<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The palace of justice opened and set to veiw [sic], in a sermon at Margarets Westminster before the Honorable House of Commons assembled in Parliament, upon the 12th of May, 1646. Being the day of their solemn thanksgiving, for regaining and taking in the several garisons, of the city of Exeter. Barnstable. Michaels Mount in Cornwall Ruthen Castle. Ilford-Combe. Aberystwyth in Wales. [double brace] Dunster Castle. Titbury Castle. Woodstock Mannor. Castle of Bridgnorth. Banbury Castle. Newarke. / By Sam. Torshel.</title>
            <author>Torshell, Samuel, 1604-1650.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 72 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A94759</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1940</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E337_12</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200826</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861461</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861461</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113598</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A94759)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113598)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 55:E337[12])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The palace of justice opened and set to veiw [sic], in a sermon at Margarets Westminster before the Honorable House of Commons assembled in Parliament, upon the 12th of May, 1646. Being the day of their solemn thanksgiving, for regaining and taking in the several garisons, of the city of Exeter. Barnstable. Michaels Mount in Cornwall Ruthen Castle. Ilford-Combe. Aberystwyth in Wales. [double brace] Dunster Castle. Titbury Castle. Woodstock Mannor. Castle of Bridgnorth. Banbury Castle. Newarke. / By Sam. Torshel.</title>
                  <author>Torshell, Samuel, 1604-1650.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 23, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.R. and E.M. for John Bellamy at the three golden Lions in Cornhill.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Order to print on verso of first leaf.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Deuteronomy XVI, 20 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Justice --  Biblical teaching --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:113598:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Palace OF JUSTICE OPENED AND SET TO VEIW, IN A SERMON At <hi>Margarets Weſtminſter</hi> before the Honorable Houſe of COMMONS Aſſembled in PARLIAMENT, upon the 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>May,</hi> 1646. Being the day of their Solemn Thankſgiving, for Regaining and taking in the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Gariſons, of
<list>
                  <item>The City of <hi>Exeter.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Barnſtable.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Michaels Mount</hi> in <hi>Cornwall</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ruthen Caſtle.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ilford-Combe.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Aberyſtwyth</hi> in <hi>Wales.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Dunſter Caſtle.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Titbury Caſtle.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Woodſtock Mannor.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Caſtle</hi> of <hi>Bridgnorth.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Banbury Caſtle.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Newarke.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>By SAM. TORSHEL.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Prov. 14.13.</hi>
               </bibl> Righteouſneſſe exalteth a Nation.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T.R.</hi> and <hi>E.M.</hi> for <hi>John Bellamy</hi> at the three golden Lions in Cornhill. 1646.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:113598:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:113598:2"/>
            <head>TO THE HONORABLE HOUSE OF COMMONS Aſſembled in PARLIAMENT.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S moſt men have cenſured the</hi> Florentine, <hi>to be</hi> Not honeſt, <hi>So I could hardly allow him (So much as in the</hi> vulgar notion) <hi>the name of</hi> A Chriſtian, <hi>when I met with theſe paſſages in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m. One, in his Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Book,</hi> De Republica, <hi>cap. 29.</hi> Si rerum viciſſitudinem Contemplemur, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periemas multa accidere ex fato ita ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gente, ut iis obviam ire nemo poſſit, quamvis in promptu re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>media fuerint. <hi>Another to the ſame purpoſe, in his Book</hi> De principe, <hi>cap. 25.</hi> Haud illud mihi obſcurum eſt, ejus Sententia complures eſſe, ac olim fuiſſe, itae rerum humana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum procurationem à fortuna omnino, ab ipſoque dec teneri, ut ab hominum prudentia nulla ratione corrigi queat: immo nullo poſſe occurri remedia. Ob id exiſtimeri poſſet, in iis re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus non multum laborandum eſſe, ſed qua fortuna impellit, co
<pb facs="tcp:113598:3"/>ſe ferri permittendum. Haec opinio majori perſuaſione his no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtris temporibus, propter rerum multiplicem converſionem, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepta eſt: quod nunquam non viſae ſint, quotidieque videan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur mutationes, extra omnem humanam, quae poſſit capi, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecturam. Hoc ego nonnunquam animo cum cogitaſſem, ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qua ex parte co inclinaveram ſententiae. Sed ne arbitrium noſtrum extinguatur, eam opinionem ſequor, ut alteram no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrarum rerum partem fortunae arbitratu judicem procurari, alteram vel paulo minus adminiſtrandam relinqui. Fortunam enim montano flumini omnia proſternenti comparare ſoleo, quod cum praeceps fertur, inagros effunditur, arbores ſternit, convellit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>què domos; hinc terrae multum abripiens, alio idem illud re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerit, omnia item prae ſe agit, omnia ejus conſpectum fugi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant, omnia illius furori cedunt, ſublata omni, qua poſſit ratione reprimi: nihilominus cum tali feratur ingenio, nihil impedit, quo minus homines pacatioribus temporibus poſſint objicibus, aggeribuſque proſpicere, ut iterum exundans cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libus deſtuat, aut impetu. repreſſo, tam effuſe pernicioſeque non feratur. Idem accidit de fortuna, quae vim ſuam exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, ubi nulla adeſt ad reſiſtendum inſtructa virtus: eò ſuos impetus convertit, ubi nullos aggeres, nulla impedimenta, qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ſibi obviam iri poſſit, novit eſſe extructa. <hi>He afterwards propounds the troubles of</hi> Italy <hi>a little before, and about his time, as an inſtance of this</hi> diſcourſe, <hi>in which he gives</hi> more <hi>to</hi> Fate; <hi>and yet to</hi> Divine ordination, leſſe; <hi>then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes one that is in profeſſion a</hi> Chriſtian. <hi>And there are others who ſpeak of the</hi> alterations <hi>and</hi> period's <hi>of</hi> King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, <hi>as if they did beleeve a</hi> Mathematicall <hi>or</hi> Chaldaick neceſſity, <hi>or a</hi> Stoick-fate, <hi>both of which do ſubject even</hi> God <hi>himſelf, one to the</hi> Starres, <hi>the other to the</hi> connex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion of ſecond Cauſes. <hi>And there are ſome men, (whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever their faith be in this,) that yet are buſie enough, to work by this advantage, upon</hi> weak <hi>and</hi> jealous apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>which are ſufficient to give countenance in the world to</hi> pretended <hi>and</hi> artificiall propheſies, <hi>which have their greateſt authority from ſuperſtitious fear.</hi> Guicciardin <hi>gives us a notable inſtance of this. There were ſome that had given out many</hi> Prognoſtications <hi>which were purpoſely made
<pb facs="tcp:113598:3"/>in favour of</hi> Charles <hi>the Emperour, and in prejudice of the</hi> French King <hi>and</hi> Nation. <hi>Theſe wrought ſo farre upon the</hi> Marqueſſe <hi>of</hi> Saluzze, <hi>that notwithſtanding his deep ingagements to</hi> Francis the firſt, <hi>and contrary to his</hi> own greateſt intereſſe, <hi>yea and to his proper</hi> inclination <hi>and</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, <hi>he fell off from his</hi> Maſter <hi>to the</hi> Emperour, <hi>after he had ſhewed his</hi> affrightment <hi>to his private freinds to whom he had complained of the</hi> inevitable Miſeries <hi>which the</hi> Fates <hi>had prepared againſt</hi> France. <hi>But we have a clear rule in</hi> Scripture <hi>by which to order our ſelves, and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe our weak fears. There we learn, that all things are indeed under a</hi> Sentence, <hi>which carries, not a</hi> neceſſity <hi>of</hi> coaction, <hi>but of</hi> Infallibility. <hi>We ſubſcribe to that of</hi> David, <hi>1</hi> Chron. <hi>29.11.</hi> Thine O Lord is the greatneſſe, and the power, and the glory, and the victory, and the maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty; for all that is in the heaven, and in the earth is thine: thine is the Kingdome, O Lord, and thou art exalted as head above all. Both riches and honour come of thee, and thou reighneſt over all, and in thine hand is power, and might, and in thine hand it is to make great. <hi>We finde there al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the courſe that this</hi> great <hi>and</hi> abſolute Soveraigne <hi>taketh, and conſtantly keepeth in the</hi> advancing <hi>and</hi> ruining <hi>of Kingdoms, which is that which</hi> Jeremiah <hi>tells the</hi> King <hi>and</hi> Princes <hi>of</hi> Judah <hi>of;</hi> cap. <hi>22.2.3, 4,</hi> &amp;c. Hear the word of the Lord, O King of Judah, that ſitteſt upon the Throne of <hi>David,</hi> thou and thy ſervants, and thy people that enter in by theſe gates. Thus ſaith the Lord, execute yee Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Righteouſneſſe, and deliver the ſpoiled out of the hand of the oppreſſor, and do no wrong, do no violence to the ſtranger, the fatherleſſe, nor the widow, neither ſhed innocent bloud in this place. For if you do this thing indeed, then ſhall there enter by the gates of this houſe, Kings ſitting upon the Throne of <hi>David,</hi> riding in Charets, and on horſes, he, and his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and his people. But if yee will not hear theſe words, I ſwear by my ſelf, ſaith the Lord, that this houſe ſhall become a deſolation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>According to the tenour of theſe words, I have</hi> preached righteouſneſſe <hi>unto you, that you may be</hi> eſtabliſhed, <hi>and that all your late</hi> Victories <hi>may bee confirmed unto your po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity.
<pb facs="tcp:113598:4"/>I might ſpeak ſomething of theſe</hi> preſent joy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>of things, in a</hi> conjecturall <hi>and</hi> prudentiall <hi>way, I am a</hi> Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant <hi>in the</hi> principles <hi>that</hi> diſtinguiſh <hi>both from</hi> Romaniſus <hi>and</hi> Schiſm, <hi>and in my</hi> Intereſſe <hi>I am a very</hi> Engliſhman. <hi>Be juſt in all things, and yee ſhall not need to fear, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> Starres, <hi>or</hi> Prophecies, <hi>or</hi> men. <hi>Let me ſpeak as a</hi> Divine, <hi>in the words of the ſon of</hi> Oded, <hi>Hear yee me in this,</hi> The Lord is with you, while yee be with him, But if yee forſake him, he will forſake you.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your faithfull, and moſt humble ſervant SAM. TORSHEL.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113598:4"/>
            <head>THE PALACE OF JUSTICE.</head>
            <head type="sub">The TEXT.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>DEUT. 16.20.</hi>
                  </bibl> Juſtice, Juſtice, <hi>or,</hi> That which is altogether juſt ſhalt thou follow, that thou mayeſt live, and inherit the land which the Lord thy God giveth thee.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Ee thinks I may uſe to you this day (<hi>Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red</hi> and <hi>Beloved</hi>) the laſt words which this great man <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpake publickly to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> which are mentioned in the 33. Chapter of this Book, ver. 29. <hi>Happy art thou, O Iſrael; who is like unto thee, O people ſaved by the Lord, the ſhield of thy help, and who is the ſword of thine excellency? thine enemies ſhall be found lyars unto thee, and thou ſhalt tread upon their high places.</hi> You are a people ſaved this day, your enemies crouch, flatter, and lie unto you, you have trod upon their <hi>high</hi> and <hi>fortified</hi> places. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides all heretofore regained, now of late you have trod upon their high place, the fortified <hi>Mount in Cornwall,</hi> upon the ſtrong Citie of <hi>Exeter,</hi> upon <hi>Barnſtable</hi> her neighbour, upon the Fort of <hi>Ilford-Comb,</hi> upon the <hi>Caſtles</hi> of <hi>Ruthein, Aberiſtwith, Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, Titbury,</hi> and <hi>Bridgnorth,</hi> upon the gariſon'd <hi>Manner</hi> of <hi>Woodſtoock,</hi> ſpecified in the <hi>firſt</hi> Order of your <hi>Honourable Houſe</hi> for calling this Aſſemblie together, beſides what is in your <hi>Addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall Order</hi> of yeſterday; you have trod upon the ſtrong <hi>Caſtle</hi> of <hi>Banbury,</hi> and the moſt conſiderable in land <hi>Gariſon</hi> of <hi>Newark.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:113598:5"/>
            <p> And that I may reflect upon my Text, <hi>You live;</hi> and God be praiſed that you doe <hi>live,</hi> after ſo many attempts againſt you; and at laſt it may now be rightly ſaid, <hi>Yee inherit the land.</hi> May I have liberty (if not to expreſſe my conceit upon the place, which yet I know ſome wiſe and learned men doe, that it is in a ſenſe literally to be applyed to theſe times, the warres of which they think doe tend toward the preparing of the <hi>Kingdome</hi> of the <hi>Saints</hi> here on earth; yet at leaſt) to allude to that Text, <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.28, 29. and to apply to you that have been faithfull in this great cauſe in hand, what our Lord ſaid, <hi>Yee are they which have continued with mee in my tentations; and I appoint unto you a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</hi> This <hi>kingdome,</hi> poſſeſſed in great part of late by the ſonnes of violence, now is in your hand, and lyes before you in a free view. Let mee have the honour in your happy company, as one of the meaneſt in your <hi>train,</hi> to goe up with you this day to the <hi>top</hi> of <hi>Piſgah,</hi> that from thence we may look over <hi>All the land of Gilead unto Dan, and all Naphtali, and the land of Ephraim and Manaſſeh, and all the land of Judah unto the utmoſt ſea, and the South, and the plain of the valley of Jericho, the Citie of palm-trees, unto Zoar:</hi> You know the ſtory from whence I borrow the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription, <hi>Deut.</hi> 34.1, 2, 3. You may this day ſee <hi>all</hi> in a manner <hi>yours;</hi> from the <hi>Mount in Cornwall,</hi> even unto <hi>Berwick,</hi> the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt <hi>Engliſh limit.</hi> May wee with thankfull hearts a little ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey the <hi>Land which the Lord our God hath given us</hi> (as it were this day) <hi>to inherit. Michaels Mount</hi> brings you in the riches of the <hi>Tinne-mines</hi> in <hi>Cormwall.</hi> Great <hi>Exeter,</hi> neat <hi>Barnſtable,</hi> and the <hi>Comb</hi> reſtore and ſecure unto you the <hi>Cloth-trade</hi> of well-affected <hi>Devonſhire. Dunſter Caſtle,</hi> the laſt <hi>pawn</hi> of the enemy in <hi>Somer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſetſhire,</hi> delivers you the quiet poſſeſſion of that <hi>temperate</hi> and <hi>fertile County.</hi> If from thence over the ſtately <hi>Severn</hi> you look into <hi>Wales,</hi> there <hi>Aberyſtwyth</hi> in <hi>Cardigan,</hi> and <hi>Ruthin Caſtle</hi> in the rich and pleaſant <hi>Vale of Cluyd,</hi> doe this day preſent you with ſervice of that mountanous Countrey and couragious people. Shall wee thence paſſe thorow the pleaſures of <hi>Shropſhire</hi> to <hi>Bridgenorth,</hi> and ſo to <hi>Titbury,</hi> the lock of two <hi>Shires, Stafford</hi> and <hi>Derby;</hi> and to <hi>Newarke,</hi> the darling of the enemies hope? wee may ſee all in a manner yours: and <hi>Oxford</hi> almoſt deſolated, like a lodge in a wilderneſſe, having loſt the proſpect of <hi>Wood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtock
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:113598:5"/>Mannor;</hi> and <hi>Banbury Caſtle,</hi> her <hi>left arm</hi> being now cut off.</p>
            <p>But take heed that you <hi>forfeit</hi> not all this mercy, and yet <hi>loſe</hi> that good <hi>land</hi> which is given you to <hi>inherit.</hi> Receive therefore the words of this exhortation: <hi>Juſtice, juſtice,</hi> or, <hi>That which is altogether juſt ſhalt thou follow, that thou mayeſt live, and inherit the land which the Lord thy God giveth thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I reade the words ſo, <hi>Juſtice, juſtice,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Text o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened.</note> becauſe in the <hi>Originall</hi> Text, the word is doubled, <hi>Tſedek, Tſedek;</hi> and in the <hi>Chalde</hi> like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, <hi>Kuſhtha, Kuſhtha. Tremellius</hi> renders it, <hi>Juſtiſſimam juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam.</hi> The <hi>Greek Tranſlation</hi> of the <hi>Septuagint</hi> reads it <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and the <hi>Vulgar Latine</hi> followes them, <hi>Juſtè quod juſtum eſt, Thou ſhalt follow that which is juſt juſtly.</hi> Our learned Interpreters in our laſt <hi>Engliſh,</hi> have given us the full ſenſe, <hi>That which is altogether juſt;</hi> all manner of juſtice, and nothing but juſtice, thou ſhalt follow exactly, carefully, conſtantly.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That thou mayeſt live:</hi> that is, ſafely, comfortably, for ſo the phraſe is uſed ordinarily. I know not whether I need to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve it, that the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t</hi> in the <hi>Text</hi> is to be taken not <hi>cauſaliter,</hi> but <hi>conſecutivè:</hi> the meaning is, that the following of juſtice is not the <hi>cauſe</hi> of this comfortable life; but onely that this comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able life is the <hi>conſequence</hi> of the following of juſtice. There is nothing difficult in theſe or the next words: And I choſe a plain Text, that I might not need to ſpend time upon explication, but employ it more uſefully. I ſhall therefore onely conſider theſe two parts.</p>
            <p n="1">I. An Exhortation, <hi>Juſtice, juſtice,</hi> or, <hi>That which is altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther juſt ſhalt thou follow.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. Two arguments of perſwaſion: 1. <hi>That thou mayeſt live.</hi> 2. That thou mayeſt <hi>inherit the land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall not ſo much as name thoſe <hi>Propoſitions</hi> into which this <hi>Text</hi> might be <hi>reſolved;</hi> but onely attend the main drift that <hi>Moſes</hi> had, who having much converſed with this people, and knowing them to be <hi>perverſe</hi> and <hi>injurious,</hi> (as they had many <hi>principles</hi> of <hi>injuſtice</hi> among them; which a <hi>Profeſſour</hi> of <hi>Jewiſh Controverſies</hi> at <hi>Leiden</hi> (namely, <hi>Conſtantin l' Emperour</hi>) hath ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved, and hath given inſtance of in his learned piece <hi>De Legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Ebraeorum Forenſibus,</hi> upon the <hi>Firſt Code,</hi> cap. 9. ſect. 11. to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:113598:6"/>whom I referre the learned Reader,) hee having now conducted them to the borders of the <hi>land</hi> of <hi>Canaan,</hi> which they were ſhortly to poſſeſſe, that they might happily injoy it in a ſecled and ſecure ſtate, hee leaves with them this advice, <hi>Juſtice, juſtice thou ſhalt follow,</hi> &amp;c. And from this, as the full <hi>ſcope</hi> of the words, I ſhall draw forth and inſiſt upon this one <hi>Doctrine;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publick Juſtice is the foundation of Publick welfare.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Doctr.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moſes</hi> himſelf had been a notable and good <hi>Juſticer</hi> among the people of the <hi>Jewes,</hi> and they were ſo farre convinced of the benefit of his <hi>adminiſtrations,</hi> that at that time when hee was <hi>forty dayes</hi> abſent from them to receive the <hi>Law</hi> from God, me thinks the people ſpeak in <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.1. as if they thought the want of a wiſe and good <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> could not be ſupplied but by having <hi>God</hi> in his ſtead: <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>p,</hi> ſay they to <hi>Aaron, Make us gods which ſhall goe before us; for as for this Moſes, that man that brought us up out of the land of Egypt, wee wot not what is become of him.</hi> Implying, that now they miſt him, they wanted the <hi>gods,</hi> who onely could ſupply his want. <hi>God</hi> hath given his <hi>name</hi> to ſuch as you, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 82.1. And the <hi>wiſe Heathen</hi> ſo eſteemed you. Hence it was that the <hi>Babylonians</hi> built the <hi>palace</hi> where <hi>Judgements</hi> were given, in the form of <hi>Heaven,</hi> the <hi>ſtone-work</hi> of <hi>skie-coloured Saphyres,</hi> and the <hi>ceiling</hi> like <hi>clouds. Princes,</hi> or <hi>ſoveraigne States</hi> (ſuch as you are in your <hi>whole Body</hi> of <hi>Three Eſtates</hi>) do fit as the publick <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biters</hi> of <hi>juſtice,</hi> to whom, as to a moſt ſacred <hi>Altar</hi> the oppreſſed doe flie, and by whom men even in the times of ſecureſt peace are regulated.</p>
            <p>But the point that I have undertaken that I may purſue it with advantage, I ſhall 1. Explicate ſo much of it as is needfull. 2. Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer ſomething by way of proof. 3. That I may then make my ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication to you.</p>
            <p n="1">1.
<note place="margin">1. The explicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the point.</note> As for explication; It will be needfull to enquire what this <hi>Juſtice</hi> is of which wee ſpeak: It is taken, 1. <hi>Generally,</hi> for all <hi>vertue,</hi> it being an <hi>Adequation</hi> to the whole rule of Gods will, a <hi>complexion</hi> of all vertues, and ſo <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> deſcibes it to be a full keeping of all the Commandements of God. Thus <hi>unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe</hi> is taken for all <hi>ſin;</hi> ſo, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.18. men are ſaid to hold the truth in unrighteouſneſſe. 2. <hi>Particularly,</hi> it is taken onely for that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the vertue which renders to every one his due.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:113598:6"/>And they deſcribe it to be <hi>Conſtans &amp; perpetua volunt as jus f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um cuique reddendi,</hi> A conſtant and firm propenſity of will to give every one his right. It is either 1. <hi>Diſtributive,</hi> according to a <hi>Geometricall praportion,</hi> not a meer equalitle, but diſpenſing <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours</hi> and <hi>puniſhments</hi> not alike, but according to the <hi>quality</hi> of the <hi>perſons,</hi> and of their <hi>merit</hi> or <hi>demerit.</hi> Or, 2. <hi>Commutative,</hi> according to <hi>Arithmeticall proportion,</hi> as in trade, &amp;c. For I will not entertain ſo wiſe an <hi>Auditory,</hi> nor the reſt of the Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to whom I fear, it would be unuſefull, with thoſe <hi>ſubtilties</hi> of an <hi>Arithmeticall, Geometricall,</hi> and <hi>Harmonicall proportion,</hi> in which <hi>Bodin</hi> hath <hi>finely</hi> handled the nature of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> which the Reader ſhall finde in his ſixth Book, the laſt Chapter <hi>De Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publica.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But plainly, This <hi>Juſtice</hi> which I am commending, is a beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full pleaſant <hi>Virgin-princeſſe</hi> attended upon by <hi>ſeven maids</hi> of <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour:</hi> Or let me rather uſe another ſimilitude; It is a <hi>goodly</hi> built <hi>palace,</hi> ſupported upon ſeven pillars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The firſt pillar hath inſcribed upon it 'ΕΥΣΕΒΕΙΑ, <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giouſneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond pillar hath inſcribed upon it 'ΑΠΡΩΣΩΠΟ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ΑΗΨΙΛ, <hi>Impartiality.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. On the third, ΤΩΝ ΠΑΘΩΝ ΤΑΕΙΣ, <hi>An ordinate Rule of paſſions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. On the fourth, ΒΟΥΛΕΥΣΙΣ, <hi>Mature Conſultation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. On the fifth, ΦΙΛΑΛΗΘΕΙΑ, <hi>Love of Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. On the ſixth, 'ΑΔΙΑΦΘΟΡΙΑ, <hi>Incorruptneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. On the ſeaventh, ΣΩΦΡΟΣΥΝΗ, <hi>Sobrietie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pillar,</hi> Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</note> The firſt pillar ſupporting the <hi>Palace</hi> of Juſtice is inſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Godlineſſe,</hi> or <hi>Religiouſneſſe:</hi> Which is according to <hi>Jethro</hi>'s advice to <hi>Moſes, Exod.</hi> 18.21. to chuſe <hi>men fearing God.</hi> And <hi>Jehoſhaphat</hi> excellently to his Judges, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 19.6, 7. <hi>Take heed what yee doe, for yee judge not for man, but for the Lord, who is with you in the judgement; wherefore now let the fear of the Lord be upon you, take heed and doe it.</hi> Hee will eaſily be led from the courſe of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> whoſe heart departs from Gods fea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>: There muſt be an awfulneſſe of his preſence maineained. The <hi>Rabbins</hi> have a ſaying, That the <hi>Angels</hi> attend in all <hi>Judicatories.</hi> And it appears that the <hi>Aethiopians</hi> had ſuch a like apprehenſion, who,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:113598:7"/>as <hi>Franc. Alvarez</hi> relates of them, left <hi>twelve chairs</hi> empty in the <hi>Judgement place,</hi> which they ſaid were the <hi>ſeats</hi> of the <hi>Angels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2.
<note place="margin">2. <hi>Pill.</hi> Impartia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity.</note> The ſecond <hi>pillar</hi> is called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Impartiality. Jehoſhaphat</hi> ſets God himſelfe as a pattern of this, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 19.7. <hi>There is no iniquity with the Lord, nor reſpect of perſons.</hi> And ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly God provided by a law, <hi>Levit.</hi> 19.15. <hi>Yee ſhall doe no unrighteouſneſſe in judgement, thou ſhalt not reſpect the perſon of the poor, nor honour the perſon of the mighty, but in righteouſneſſe ſhalt thou judge thy neighbour.</hi> You muſt know no parents nor kindred in the cauſe of Juſtice, as that brave <hi>Spartan</hi> ſaid, that now hee was <hi>Patriae &amp; Legibus datus,</hi> hee had beſtowed himſelf upon his Countrey and the Lawes. It was a gallant <hi>return</hi> which <hi>Rutilius</hi> in the <hi>Roman</hi> ſtory made to an intimate of his: his friend having requeſted ſomewhat of him which hee counld not honeſtly grant, and paſſionately ſaying unto him, <hi>Quid tuâ mihi opus eſt amicitià, ſi non impetro quod rogo?</hi> I had as good be without tſuch a friend as have him, when I cannot obtain of him what I requeſt. Hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, <hi>Imò, quid mihi tuâ, ſi tuâ cauſâ aliquid inhoneſtè facturus ſum?</hi> I can want ſuch a friend, if for his ſake I muſt doe that which is not honeſt. Wee find an <hi>Oath</hi> in the <hi>ninth Novel</hi> of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinians Inſtitutions,</hi> againſt addicting to either partie, and he that is in office, not onely ſwears, but layes himſelfe under a deep <hi>curſe</hi> in that caſe, <hi>Let mee have my part with Judas, and let the leproſie of Gehezi, and the trembling of Cain come upon mee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3.
<note place="margin">3. <hi>Pill.</hi> The rule of paſſions.</note> The third <hi>pillar</hi> is called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>An ordinate Rule of affections.</hi> Anger, hatred, love, envie, revenge muſt be left with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out in the <hi>porch,</hi> when a man goes in to the <hi>palace</hi> of <hi>Juſtice;</hi> but chiefly <hi>partiall favour</hi> and <hi>fear.</hi> It is among the characters of a Ruler, <hi>Exod.</hi> 18.21. They muſt be <hi>men of courage.</hi> A coward (wee ſay) cannot be an honeſt man: frowns or threats will by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſſe him. I remember ſometime to have taken notice of it, in the diligent and curious <hi>Collection</hi> which <hi>Anſelm de Boodt</hi> hath made of the <hi>Symbols</hi> of Princes and other eminent men, that <hi>Nicolas</hi> the <hi>Third, Marques</hi> of <hi>Eſté</hi> and <hi>Ferrara</hi> had in his, <hi>A pillar</hi> (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenting Fortitude) erected and ſtanding firm in the midſt of the flowing waves, but embraced with a <hi>Key,</hi> (the embleme of faithfulneſſe, The key keeps Treaſures ſafely, and locks up Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords:) and a <hi>ſword,</hi> (ſignifying Juſtice) and the word was, <hi>In fide
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:113598:7"/>&amp; juſtitia Fortitudo;</hi> implying, that a man that hath not courage cannot be faithfull and juſt, and that no man is couragious but hee that alſo is honeſt.</p>
            <p n="4">4.<note place="margin">4. <hi>Pill.</hi> Delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> The fourth <hi>pillar</hi> is called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Mature Deliberation.</hi> This <hi>Virgin-lady Juſtice</hi> hath not a giddy running haſte, but a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, matronlike grave pace; indeed ſhee delayes not unneceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: Thoſe Judges deſerved the puniſhment which <hi>Theodorick</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted on them, who having put off the ſuit of a poor widow di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers yeers, but upon her petition to <hi>Theodorick,</hi> and his command to them, having diſpatched it in two dayes, when they came to him with expectation of thanks for their ſpeed, hee cenſured them deeply: becauſe ſeeing it appeared that they could, yet they had not diſpatched it ſooner. But in caſes eſpecially of puniſhment, it much becometh Juſtice to be mature, adviſed, and wary. See that one notable place, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.4. in caſe of <hi>Information</hi> about <hi>falſe worſhip,</hi> how <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpeaks for directing the ſentence that is to be given; <hi>If it be told thee, and thou haſt heard of it, and enquired diligently, and behold it be true, and the thing certain, — Then ſhalt thou bring forth that man,</hi> &amp;c. See how many words are here heaped up together to prevent a raſh judgement upon a falſe ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion. It was that which much commended the <hi>integrity</hi> of <hi>Job,</hi> who profeſſeth, <hi>Job</hi> 29.16. <hi>The cauſe which I knew not I ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched out.</hi> And even <hi>Feſtus</hi> himſelf, though an <hi>Heathen,</hi> proceeded upon this principle, when hee ſaid, (<hi>Acts</hi> 25.16.) <hi>It is not the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the Romans to deliver any man to die, before that hee which is accuſed have the accuſers face to face, and have licence to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer for himſelf concerning the crime laid againſt him.</hi> Agreeable to this, it was a memorable ſentence of <hi>Seneca</hi> the <hi>Tragoedian</hi> in his <hi>Medea; Qui ſtatuit aliquid, parte inauditâ alterâ, aequum licet ſtatuerit, haud aequus fuit:</hi> That though a mans ſentence be right, yet hee is not right in giving it, if he give it before either party be heard.</p>
            <p n="5">5.<note place="margin">5. <hi>Pill.</hi> The love of Truth.</note> The fifth <hi>pillar</hi> is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>The love of Truth.</hi> This was alſo <hi>Jethro</hi>'s advice, <hi>Exod.</hi> 18.21. to chuſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>men of truth.</hi> And of this the Prophet ſpeaks, <hi>Zech.</hi> 8.16. <hi>Execute the judgement of truth and peace in your gates.</hi> Of the preſervation of which, ſome of the wiſer Heathens were ſo tender, that it was a Law in the great Court of the <hi>Axcopagitae,</hi> that hee that was to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:113598:8"/>plead before them, was to plead <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>without either paſſion or preface,</hi> leſt the mindes of the Judges might be inflamed into an unjuſt indignation, or ſoftned into too much pity.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">6. <hi>Pill.</hi> Incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptneſſe.</note> The ſixth <hi>pillar</hi> is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Incorruptneſſe,</hi> in the hatred of Bribes: which is required in that place of Scripture which I have oft commended unto you, <hi>Exed.</hi> 18.21. Men <hi>hating covetonſneſſe.</hi> The <hi>Theban Greeks</hi> had this meaning, among whom the <hi>Statues</hi> of their <hi>Judges</hi> were erected <hi>without hands.</hi> But the evidence of the <hi>Scripture</hi> is much ſtronger, and fuller of authority againſt the corruption of gifts, as that of <hi>Solomon,</hi> Prov. 15.27. <hi>Hee that is greedy of gain troubleth his own houſe: but hee that hateth gifts ſhall live.</hi> And <hi>Job</hi> 15.34. <hi>Fire ſhall conſume the Tabernacles of Bribery.</hi> Beſides much that might be inſiſted upon to that purpoſe.</p>
            <p n="7">7.
<note place="margin">7. <hi>Pill.</hi> Sobriety.</note> The laſt <hi>pillar</hi> hath this inſcription upon it, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brietie;</hi> which is alſo very neceſſary, ſeeing the Prophet ſaith, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4.11. <hi>Whoredom, and wine, and new wine take away the heart.</hi> And therefore among thoſe prudent inſtructions which the <hi>Mother</hi> of <hi>Lemuel</hi> gave him, this was one, <hi>Prov.</hi> 31.4, 5. <hi>It is not for Kings, O Lemuel, it is not for Kings to drink wine, nor for Princes ſtrong drink, leſt they drink and forget the Law, and pervert the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of any of the afflicted.</hi> But I remember to whom I am ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, a Society of grave and wiſe men, whoſe conſtant and almoſt <hi>hourly</hi> attendance upon the publick exigents, will not give them leiſure to be intemperate.</p>
            <p>This is the <hi>Palace</hi> of <hi>Juſtice</hi> thus ſupported:
<note place="margin">Acts of Juſtice.</note> Let us onely for a ſhort time enter into the <hi>Great Court</hi> to obſerve the tranſacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons there; which are principally the Diſpenſations of <hi>Rewards</hi> and <hi>Puniſhments:</hi> theſe are the two great <hi>engines</hi> of a State. The <hi>Roman Common-wealth,</hi> before it changed into a <hi>Monarchy,</hi> grew illuſtrious this way, requiring a ſevere account according to the Lawes, and according to mens <hi>demerits,</hi> and giving prayſes, tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphs, and places of gain or truſt to well-deſervers. I finde all <hi>Law-books</hi> full of <hi>penalties,</hi> but little publiſhed concerning re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards: whether it be, 1. Becauſe good men are ſcarce: Or, 7. Becauſe States finde it more profitable and cheap, to reſtrain by fear, then encourage by reward, becauſe Vertue is it ſelfe a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:113598:8"/>to the good and wiſe. Or, 3. Becauſe <hi>Princes</hi> and <hi>Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign States</hi> think it beſt to keep the liberty in their own breaſts to reward, that it may appear more <hi>free,</hi> that it may more bind, that penalties may ſeem only to flow from the Lawes, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards from <hi>Bounty.</hi> But both are neceſſary.</p>
            <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">1. Puniſhments.</note> There muſt be a <hi>zeal</hi> of <hi>juſtice</hi> againſt publick demerits. It was an <hi>Aphoriſme</hi> of <hi>Lewis</hi> the 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> That a <hi>Prince</hi> who puniſheth not a <hi>crime</hi> where he may <hi>doe</hi> it, is no leſſe guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty then he that perpetrated it. The <hi>guilty</hi> muſt be condemned, though it be done (as <hi>Bias</hi> profeſſed of himſelf) <hi>weeping.</hi> To which that of <hi>Solomon</hi> anſwereth, <hi>Prov.</hi> 20.8. <hi>A King that ſitteth on the throne of judgement, ſcattereth away all evill with his eyes.</hi> The eyes of <hi>Juſtice</hi> as lovely and as pleaſant as they are, are yet <hi>red fierie eyes</hi> towards them that deſerve ill; for God ſet up Magiſtracy to be a terrour to evill doers, and that as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. he ſhould not bear the <hi>Sword in vain.</hi> But I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, that it is not ſo proper for a <hi>Preacher</hi> of the Goſpel of <hi>Chriſts Kingdom</hi> of peace, to call for the drawing of the Sword; but the people from all parts of the Country, who have bin plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, waſted, oppreſſed, doe, and may cry aloud, <hi>Juſtice, Juſtice,</hi> as they have done alſo formerly with good ſucceſſe. But it is enough to have given an intimation. <hi>Verbum ſapienti ſat eſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">2. Rewards.</note> 
               <hi>Rewards</hi> are alſo to be thought on. <hi>Honour</hi> beſtowed upon unworthy men is made cheap and deſpiſed. When <hi>Flavius</hi> a <hi>free-man</hi> was without merit made an <hi>Aedile,</hi> the <hi>Patricians</hi> and <hi>Nobles</hi> caſt off their Enſignes of their orders with indignation. You have been ſenſible in ſome of your <hi>Votes</hi> who hath been faulty in this, even unto prodigality. But the wiſer of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then were <hi>tender</hi> even of the very honour of puniſhments. You know the cuſtome which they had at <hi>Athens</hi> of baniſhing brave men by <hi>Oſtraciſme,</hi> when by reaſon of their power or the reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their vertue, the City had reaſon, or ſeemed to have rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to fear them, ſo that the very <hi>baniſhment.</hi> of theſe men was to their honour. This cuſtome was abrogated on this occaſion, when one <hi>Hyperbolus</hi> an infamous and vile perſon was ſo baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. But I ſpeak to them who are able to judge of merits, and are juſt in the <hi>owning</hi> of them. It is indeed the obſervation of <hi>poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall men,</hi> that weak and jealous <hi>Princes,</hi> and corrupt and ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:113598:9"/>
               <hi>Times,</hi> cannot endure the <hi>luſtre</hi> of <hi>Reputation</hi> in others, which themſelves want. Hence <hi>Domitian</hi> ſought to ruine all that were brave and well eſteemed. But you have ſo much luſtre in regard of your publike ingagement, your diligence wiſdome and faithfulneſſe in it, that you need not to fear, to honour and reward others, who are the ſervants of your juſt and honourable commands.</p>
            <p>But it is time I proceed to the ſecond thing that I propoſed,
<note place="margin">2. The proof of the point.</note> The <hi>proof</hi> of this point which we have in hand. And it may be made good, that <hi>Juſtice,</hi> (that publike juſtice which we have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed) is the <hi>foundation of the publike welfare;</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. By the direct evidences of other Scriptures.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By ſome particular Reaſons.</p>
            <p n="3">3. By an illuſtration from the contrary.</p>
            <p n="1">1.
<note place="margin">1. By the Script.</note> The Scriptures are clear in the proof of it. If we had but that one Text, <hi>Prov.</hi> 14.34. it were enough, a <hi>Text</hi> worthy to be written upon the dore of a <hi>Parliament-Houſe</hi> in letters of gold, <hi>Righteouſneſſe exalteth a Nation, but ſinne</hi> (the ſin of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice he means) <hi>is a reproach to any people.</hi> As that other to be written over the <hi>Kings State,</hi> in the <hi>Houſe of Peers,</hi> Prov. 16.12. <hi>The Throne is eſtabliſhed by righteouſneſſe.</hi> But I adde alſo two other <hi>Aphoriſmes</hi> of that wiſe King, <hi>Prov.</hi> 4.18. <hi>The path of the juſt is as the ſhining light, that ſhineth more and more unto the perfect day,</hi> Prov. 12.7. <hi>The wicked are overthrown and are not: but the houſe of the righteous ſhall ſtand.</hi> I may adde thoſe expreſſions of the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah, Iſ.</hi> 54.14. <hi>In righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe ſhalt thou be eſtabliſhed: thou ſhalt be farre from oppreſſion, for thou ſhalt not fear: and from terrour, for it ſhall not come near thee.</hi> And <hi>Iſ.</hi> 33.15.16. <hi>He that walketh righteouſly, and ſpeaketh uprightly, he that deſpiſeth the gain of oppreſſions, that ſhaketh hie hands from holding of bribes, that ſtoppeth his ears from hearing of bloud, and ſhutteth his eyes from ſeeing evill: He ſhall dwell on high, his place of defence ſhall be the munition of rocks, bread ſhall be given him, his waters ſhall be ſure.</hi> I ſhall conclude theſe teſtimonies with that application which is made in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> unto <hi>Shallum, Jer.</hi> 22.15, 16. <hi>Shalt thou reign becauſe thou cloſeſt thy ſelf in Cedar? Did not thy father eate and drink, and doe judgement and juſtice, and then it was well
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:113598:9"/>with him? He judged the cauſe of the poor and needy, then it was well with him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">2. By Reaſons.</note> But beſides theſe direct evidences, we may ſee the truth of the point, in ſome particular grounds of it. I will inſtance in four of them.</p>
            <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">1. Becauſe <hi>Juſtice</hi> makes acceptable to God.</note> 
               <hi>Juſtice</hi> is the foundation of welfare, becauſe it maketh <hi>men</hi> and <hi>States acceptable</hi> to God on whoſe pleaſure, we do all ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, that publike welfare depends. He it is, who hath <hi>wiſdome</hi> and <hi>might,</hi> as <hi>Daniel</hi> tells the great King, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.20, 21. <hi>He changeth the times and the ſeaſons, he removeth Kings, and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth up Kings.</hi> This great God that rules the Nations, takes a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall care for them that are juſt: of which we have an antient ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, <hi>Gen.</hi> 7.1. where God ſaith unto <hi>Noah, Come thou and all thy houſe into the Arke, for thee have I ſeen righteous before me in this generation.</hi> And the Prophet <hi>Eſaiah</hi> gives another notable example, of one to whoſe poſterity God ſubdued the people of <hi>Canaan, Eſ.</hi> 41.2. <hi>He raiſed up the righteous man</hi> (meaning <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham) from the Eaſt, called him to his foct, gave the Nations be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him,</hi> (underſtand it of his poſterity,) <hi>and made him Ruler over Kings: he gave them as the duſt to his ſword, and as driven ſtubble to his bow.</hi> So true is that of the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> which hitheto may be applyed, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.17, 18. <hi>The Kingdom of God is inrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe and peace; he that in theſe things ſerveth Chriſt, is accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to God, and approved of men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">2. Becauſe <hi>Juſtice</hi> is the Nurſe of Peace.</note> Publike proſperity is <hi>nurſed</hi> up by <hi>peace,</hi> and <hi>peace</hi> is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured and preſerved by Juſtice: according to that of the <hi>Pſalmiſt, Pſal.</hi> 85.10. <hi>Righteouſneſſe and peace have kiſſed each other.</hi> And in another Pſalm, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 72.2. <hi>The mountains ſhall bring peace to the people, and the little hills by righteouſneſſe.</hi> Are there any aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults againſt the ſetled <hi>peace? Juſtice</hi> it is that fortifies againſt them. <hi>The righteous ſhall hold on his way, and he that hath clean hands ſhall be ſtronger and ſtronger, Job.</hi> 17.9. Doth any ſide lye open to danger? <hi>Juſtice</hi> doth ſurround us. <hi>Thou Lord wilt bleſſe the righteous</hi> (ſaith <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 5.12.) <hi>with favour wilt thou com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe him as with a ſheild.</hi> Is there any thing that may annoy, like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to come in by the <hi>back dore?</hi> Juſtice alſo keeps that. For which the <hi>Prophet</hi> is expreſſe, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 58.8. <hi>Thy righteouſneſſe ſhall go before thee, the glory of the</hi> Lord ſhall be thy <hi>Rere-ward;</hi> or as
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:113598:10"/>the <hi>Margin</hi> there hath well rendred it according to the <hi>Hebrew,</hi> It ſhall <hi>gather thee up,</hi> So to bring thee off ſafely. In a word, what doth more threaten the publike quiet, then a <hi>publike diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content</hi> by reaſon of oppreſſions? when as it is, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 5.7. <hi>The Lord looks for judgment, but behold oppreſſion; for righteouſneſſe, but behold a cry.</hi> But that very <hi>Text</hi> doth intimate the <hi>ſafety</hi> of a <hi>State,</hi> where there is no <hi>oppreſſion,</hi> but <hi>judgment</hi> and <hi>righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> there is no <hi>cry,</hi> no diſcontent.</p>
            <p n="3">3.
<note place="margin">3. Becauſe <hi>Juſtice</hi> maintains Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</note> The quiet management of <hi>Authority</hi> and <hi>Power</hi> is maintain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>Reputation;</hi> how elſe ſhould ſuch huge vaſte <hi>Bodies</hi> of people, be <hi>led</hi> and <hi>ruled</hi> by a <hi>few?</hi> But <hi>Juſtice</hi> it is that gives and keeps up <hi>Reputation</hi> and an <hi>Awe</hi> in the differing minds of multitudes. This is it that <hi>ſteales</hi> the hearts of men. That <hi>Ambitious</hi> young Prince, <hi>Abſalom,</hi> knew that it was the moſt <hi>taking</hi> argument, when he had a deſigne to transferre the government from the old King upon himſelf, <hi>O</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>that I were made Judge in the Land, that every man which had any ſuite or cauſe, might come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, and I would doe him Juſtice!</hi> 2 Sam. 15.4. And it is ſaid in the ſixth verſe, <hi>So</hi> Abſalom <hi>ſtole the hearts of the men of Iſrael.</hi> For as in the place before mentioned, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.17, 18. He that doth this, is not only acceptable to God, but <hi>approved of men.</hi> It is among the higheſt bleſſings which God promiſeth to a <hi>reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed State,</hi> when he hath purged away the droſſe, and taken away all the tinne; when he hath reſtored the Judges as at the firſt, and the Councellors as at the beginning, that then they ſhall have the reputation of being a <hi>juſt State, Eſ.</hi> 1.26. <hi>Thou ſhalt be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, The City of righteouſneſſe, The faithfull City.</hi> And it is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved alſo by the ſame means; for ſaith <hi>Solomon, Prev.</hi> 10.7. <hi>The memory of the juſt is bleſſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4.
<note place="margin">4. Becauſe <hi>Juſtice</hi> builds up families</note> A Kingdom is a combination of <hi>families;</hi> and they are <hi>built up,</hi> and kept together by <hi>juſt dealing.</hi> The wiſe King had obſerved it, <hi>Prov.</hi> 20.7. <hi>The juſt man walketh in his intergrity, his children are bleſſed after him.</hi> And in another place, <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.33. <hi>The curſe of the Lord is in the houſe of the wicked: but he bleſſeth the habitation of the juſt.</hi> To this purpoſe we have a rich and ſure promiſe, <hi>Eſ.</hi> 32.17, 18, 19. <hi>The work of righteouſneſſe ſhall be peace, and the effect of righteouſneſſe quietneſſe and aſſurance for ever. And my people ſhall dwell in a peaceable habitation, and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:113598:10"/>in ſure dwellings, and in quiet reſting places: when it ſhal hayle, coming down on the forreſt; and the City ſhall be low in a low place.</hi> Nay, and beyond this, ſometimes a few <hi>families,</hi> yea a few <hi>perſons</hi> that are righteous, are the <hi>publike ſecurity. Abraham</hi> knew that it was farre from God to ſlay the <hi>righteous</hi> with the wicked: and <hi>God</hi> confirms him by his word, <hi>If I find in</hi> Sodom, <hi>fifty righteous within the City, then I will ſpare all the place for their ſakes.</hi> Gen. 18.26. He comes, <hi>v.</hi> 28. to <hi>forty ſive, v.</hi> 29. to <hi>forty, v.</hi> 30. to <hi>thirty, v.</hi> 31. to <hi>twenty, v.</hi> 32. to <hi>ten.</hi> Then <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> could go no lower. But God doth, in the caſe of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> even to <hi>one, Jer.</hi> 5.1. <hi>See, if yee can find a man, if there be any that executeth judgement, that ſeeketh the truth, and I will par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3.
<note place="margin">3. By the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, That Injuſtice ruines a State.</note> There is yet one other proof which I ſhall offer of this point, namely the illuſtration of it from the contrary, That <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice undermines the publike proſperity, and makes a State vile and weak.</hi> For the confirmation of this, among many Scriptures that might be alledged, I would commend the ſerious reading of that whole <hi>period, Jer.</hi> 22. from <hi>v.</hi> 1. to <hi>v.</hi> 10. which I ſhall ſpare to recite; It is the <hi>Prophets</hi> grave and wholſome application of himſelf in the <hi>Lords name,</hi> to the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Judah</hi> and his <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</hi> Only give me leave to make uſe of one paſſage of the <hi>Pſalmiſt's, Pſal.</hi> 75.2, 3. <hi>When I ſhall receive the Congregation, I will judge uprightly. The earth and all the Inhabitants thereof are diſſolved: I bear up the pillars of it.</hi> I know not whether <hi>David</hi> made this <hi>Pſalm,</hi> but the ſpeech is very like his, and it was a Prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like and juſt reſolution what courſe to take, when he ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the government, of which he had the expectation; and the <hi>times</hi> he deſcribes were much like the <hi>times</hi> of <hi>Saul,</hi> when <hi>All</hi> was <hi>diſſolved,</hi> or, as it is in the Hebrew, <hi>Melted.</hi> Without <hi>Juſtice</hi> all things <hi>melt,</hi> and fall aſunder. The Similitude is from the melt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of things <hi>heterogeneous,</hi> as when little ſticks, ſtraws, feathers, are <hi>frozen</hi> up together with the water into one <hi>Cake</hi> of <hi>Ice,</hi> when it <hi>melts,</hi> they all are looſened from each other, and go their ſeverall wayes: as a mixt body alſo made up of <hi>lead, tin, ſilver, &amp;c.</hi> But that which is <hi>homogeneous</hi> though it be looſened, is not diſſolved, as <hi>gold</hi> when it is melted, all the parts ſtill are <hi>gold.</hi> But a <hi>State</hi> is a <hi>mixt body,</hi> when
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:113598:11"/>it is melted, and the bands looſened, it is loſt: the members of it are made <hi>unſerviceable</hi> and to one another a <hi>burthen:</hi> All this disorder is brought in by injuſtice. Nothing ruines a people ſooner. The <hi>Macedonian</hi> Empire had a ſpeedy erection, but it had alſo a very ſpeedy <hi>diſſolution;</hi> and <hi>Pauſanias</hi> by a naturall light could diſcern the cauſe of it, Becauſe the <hi>foundation</hi> of it was ſaid in <hi>Perjurie.</hi> We have ſeen the <hi>Palace,</hi> or the <hi>Tower</hi> rather of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> a ſtrong built and ſteddy <hi>fabrick.</hi> But the <hi>City</hi> of <hi>Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence,</hi> as one hath deſcribed it to us, is nothing but a <hi>heap</hi> of <hi>ruines, cemented</hi> with <hi>blood;</hi> a place where <hi>Earth-quakes</hi> and <hi>out-ragious winds</hi> are very frequent: where the water is <hi>poyſonous,</hi> the air in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectious: the <hi>inhabitants</hi> clothed in the skins of <hi>Lyons, Wolves, Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, Foxes,</hi> or in the ſpotted skins of <hi>Panthers.</hi> He tells us plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantly that ſome of them being <hi>diſſected</hi> were found to have <hi>two hearts,</hi> whereby a Judgment might be made of all the reſt of the <hi>Inhabitants.</hi> Nothing worſhipt there, but thoſe <hi>tria numina, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, gain,</hi> and <hi>luſt.</hi> The <hi>Trade</hi> they drive, only <hi>Boxes</hi> of <hi>Smoak, Vizards, counterfeit ware,</hi> or <hi>poyſons, racks, halters,</hi> or <hi>falſe Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences,</hi> pretended <hi>Patents, &amp;c.</hi> He tells us alſo, that about the houſes were heard nothing but <hi>Ravens</hi> and <hi>ſhreich-Owles;</hi> and in the ſtreets were obſerved divers <hi>ſtanding pooles,</hi> filled up with the <hi>tears</hi> of poor <hi>widowes,</hi> young wronged <hi>Orphan's,</hi> and <hi>poor men</hi> oppreſſed by the rich and mighty.</p>
            <p>But this confuſed building cannot ſtand. Such a ſtructure weighs down it ſelf; and all the <hi>Pillars</hi> upon which it is propped, are rotten.</p>
            <p>May you pleaſe now after you have ſeen the <hi>beauty</hi> and <hi>ſtrength</hi> of thoſe <hi>ſeven Pillars</hi> ſupporting the <hi>Palace</hi> of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> to take a ſhort view of thoſe unfound <hi>props</hi> of the ruinous building of <hi>Injuſtice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">1. For a man to live to himſelf, an unſound prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple.</note> One is, That <hi>principle</hi> of worldly yea and <hi>divelliſh</hi> wiſdom, that I may borrow a <hi>Character</hi> from the <hi>Apoſtle James,</hi> which is this: <hi>That a man ſhould doe all for himſelf, and make his own In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt the god whom he ſerves.</hi> This is the <hi>Trojan horſe</hi> that being let into the world, bears in the belly of it <hi>fire, ſword, facriledge, plunder, deſolation.</hi> That man that ſerves himſelf, cares not to ruine all the world beſides. <hi>Self-love,</hi> when it overflowes its chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell, overthrowes all things that ſtand in its way, and bears down
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:113598:11"/>all reſpects of <hi>duty, honeſty,</hi> and <hi>relation.</hi> Theſe men are they that turn the world upſide down. We have known ſuch men make no <hi>conſcience</hi> to <hi>ſacrifice</hi> the <hi>blood</hi> of ſuch as have ſerved them with the greateſt devotion and paſſion, upon the <hi>Altar</hi> of <hi>ſelf-Intereſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">2. To live by fiction, anunfound principle.</note> Another, is this <hi>principle.</hi> Namely, <hi>That it is beſt, eaſieſt, and ſafeſt, for men to govern themſelves by fiction, becauſe there are few wiſe men who will attend thoſe drifts, but the greater part of people, ſuch as cannot diſcover thoſe maſqueries, and are willing to be deceived.</hi> But we that beleeve the Scriptures, know what an unſound bottome this is, where we learn, that 'tis moſt <hi>ſafe</hi> to be <hi>ſincere,</hi> and that the <hi>honeſt man</hi> is upon the ſureſt tearms for his ſtanding: for as for them, who as the <hi>Prophet</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 15.16. <hi>Seek deep to hide their councell, and whoſe works are in the dark, and ſay, Who ſeeth us? and, Who knoweth us? Surely their turning of things upſide down, ſhall be eſteemed as the Potters clay.</hi> And that memorable ſentence of <hi>Solomons, Prov.</hi> 26.27. is an abſolute truth; <hi>Who ſo diggeth a pit, ſhall fall therein: and he that rolleth a ſtone, it will return upon him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3.<note place="margin">3. To purſue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, an unſound principle.</note> A third, is this principle. <hi>That it is good to reign like Lions, to keep them down whom you have once got under, to purſue all ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages, and never to be reconciled, or to forgive.</hi> Truly a very deſperate maxime of ſuch as doe endeavour even to <hi>eterniſe</hi> their <hi>revenge,</hi> as if they had taken ſuch an <hi>Oath</hi> as <hi>Hanibals</hi> father gave him when he was young, <hi>never</hi> to be at peace with the <hi>Romans.</hi> Some there are that take even a <hi>dying pleaſure</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge. I have read a very remarkable <hi>ſtory</hi> to this purpoſe in <hi>Zonaras,</hi> of one of the Greek Emperours the inhumane <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philus,</hi> who having a prime and eminent man of a party contrary to him, then in his power, one <hi>Theophobus,</hi> when he perceived he could not live, for the approaches of <hi>death</hi> were now upon him, being loth to let him ſurvive him, he ſent for the <hi>head</hi> of his priſoner, and taking pleaſure with his eyes now almoſt ſetled by death to behold it, with his trembling weak arme he takes and handles that pale bloody head, and wraps his <hi>fingers</hi> in the <hi>locks</hi> of it, and with a triumphing de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light ſpeaks to it, <hi>'Tis true, I ſhall be no longer Theophilus, nor art thou any more Theophobus.</hi> And often repeating over theſe
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:113598:12"/>words, his laſt words, his revengfull angry unquiet ſoul expired, and with a <hi>bloody ſmile</hi> he died. But I hope I ſpeak to no men that are of ſuch a <hi>Character.</hi> Let that one only place be remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred inſtead of many, <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.13. <hi>He ſhall have judgment without mercy, that hath ſhewed no mercy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4.<note place="margin">4. To be wiſe for this life only, an unſound prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple.</note> A fourth Pillar, (and I will preſent to your view no more,) is this principle. <hi>That it is wiſdome to take care that we be well here, and to venture for hereafter; ſeeing that we cannot be mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable when we are no more.</hi> Ah wretched <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> how is it poſſible that you can reſiſt the contrary teſtimony of your own breaſts within you, the working of your own <hi>Conſciences?</hi> But we who know and beleeve, that reſpect to <hi>eternity</hi> is the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt wiſdome, need not be informed of the unſoundneſſe of this bottom. And being unwilling to detain you any longer upon ſuch an heap, for as it is not ſafe to walk among ruines, ſo the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thinking upon theſe principles may be dangerous, ſome haply may <hi>ſtumble,</hi> or ſome may get <hi>duſt</hi> in their eyes, I doe therefore haſten out of this diſcourſe, that I may paſſe on to the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> and <hi>Application of the point.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">3. The Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> Honourable and beloved, I have preſented <hi>Juſtice</hi> to you, a Virgin Princeſſe, but in a <hi>plain dreſſe</hi> that nothing might commend her to you, ſo much as her own native <hi>beauty</hi> and <hi>luſtre,</hi> only with this advantage I have preſented her, that you might ſee the <hi>hand-maids</hi> of her family, and I have ſet by her the unpleaſing and unſightly face of <hi>Injurie</hi> or <hi>Violence,</hi> as a <hi>ſpot</hi> to commend her <hi>whiteneſſe;</hi> I have no deſigne upon the point, but this one to perſwade you to love her. <hi>Juſtice, Juſtice ſhalt thou follow, &amp;c.</hi> Let me ſpeak to this.</p>
            <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">1. A generall ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation to Juſtice.</note> In generall, in the words of the Prophet, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 10.12. <hi>Sowe to your ſelves in righteouſneſſe, reap in mercy.</hi> Conſider the nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble patterns that are before you in the Scripture. Among many others I would commend two. The example of <hi>Job cap.</hi> 29. He delivered the poor that cryed, the fatherleſſe, and him that had none to help him; he cauſed the widowes heart to ſing for joy; He put on righteouſneſſe, and it clothed him, and his judgment was as a Robe and a Diadem: He was eyes to the blind, and feet to the lame: A father to the poor, and the cauſe that he knew not, he ſearched out: He brake the jawes of the wicked,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:113598:12"/>and pluket the ſpoyl out of his teeth. And the example of <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> cap. 5. Hee being the Kings <hi>Commiſſioner</hi> or the <hi>Tirſhatha,</hi> as hee is called according to the <hi>Perſian</hi> Language, <hi>Ezra</hi> 2.63. when a great cry of the people and their wives came unto him by reaſon of oppreſſours, hee was moved with it, (<hi>Nehem.</hi> 5.6.) and having adviſed with himſelfe, hee improves his authoritie for their reliefe, rebuking even the <hi>Nobles</hi> with much courage, <hi>ver.</hi> 7, 8, 9. and gives not over till hee had purchaſed the content of the poor who were wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the rich and potent men. Beſides his great equity and condeſcenſion mentioned, <hi>verſ.</hi> 14, 15, 16, 17, 18. <hi>Write</hi> after ſuch <hi>faire copies:</hi> I might abound in examples. Let <hi>Justice</hi> ſet the <hi>bounds</hi> to your power, as <hi>Pompey</hi> anſwered to <hi>Phra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>artes</hi> the King of <hi>Parthia,</hi> who deſiring by his <hi>Ambaſſadors</hi> whom hee ſent to the <hi>Roman Generall,</hi> That <hi>Euphrates</hi> might be made the <hi>period</hi> of the <hi>Roman Empire:</hi> Hee replyed, That neither <hi>Seas</hi> nor <hi>Mountains,</hi> but <hi>Justice</hi> onely ſhould ſet a <hi>Terme</hi> to them; and though they had <hi>power,</hi> yet they would goe no farther then <hi>justly</hi> they might goe. And let <hi>Juſtice</hi> have <hi>influence</hi> upon your <hi>publick Councels:</hi> Nothing is more lovely to my ſoule then the power of <hi>Christs grace</hi> manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted in the lives of <hi>Christians;</hi> yet I cannot but commend that naturall honeſty planted in the mindes of the wiſer and braver <hi>Heathens:</hi> It is related in <hi>Plutarch,</hi> That in the midſt of ſome great ſtreights wherein <hi>Athens</hi> then was, <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> ſaid hee had ſomewhat wherein to give his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion for the behoofe of the State, but that hee thought not fit to deliver himſelfe publickly: The City appointed <hi>Aristides,</hi> a man in whom they might repoſe the greateſt truſt, to heare him, and as hee ſhould think fit, to give an account of it: When hee came to make his report, hee told them, That the advice of <hi>Themistocles</hi> was indeed ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>profitable,</hi> but not <hi>honeſt:</hi> Whereupon the <hi>People</hi> would not ſo much as hear it. I need not make application of theſe <hi>Stories</hi> to ſuch wiſe men. In ſtead of enlarging this gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Exhortation, let mee pray, and let us together pray in the words of the Prophet, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.8. <hi>Drop down, yee heavens from above, and let the skies powr downs righteouſneſſe, let the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:113598:13"/>earth open, and let them bring forth ſalvation, and let righteouſneſs ſpring up together.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly,
<note place="margin">2. Particular Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortations.</note> I deſcend to ſome particulars:</p>
            <p n="1">1. <note place="margin">1. To be iuſt to God.</note> Be <hi>juſt</hi> unto God your <hi>Deliverer,</hi> who hath <hi>crowned</hi> your indeavours with all thoſe ſucceſſes which in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of my <hi>Sermon</hi> I mentioned according to your <hi>Order</hi> for the duty of the <hi>day.</hi> Put all your ſtrength to this Cauſe: Settle <hi>Religion</hi> with your firſt care. I ſpare to be particular, becauſe you have a godly and learned <hi>Aſſembly</hi> to adviſe you.</p>
            <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Be <hi>just</hi> to your <hi>publick promiſes,</hi> to the <hi>Nationall Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant</hi> into which you have ſolemnly entred, in which you have lifted up your <hi>hands</hi> to the <hi>High God.</hi> I know that many come hither to theſe <hi>Sermons,</hi> to gather up angry paſſages from the <hi>Preachers</hi> before you: there is a generation of ill-affected men that would have it ſo. But I have nothing wherein to <hi>chide,</hi> nor if I had, were this a day for it; This day is made up of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but joyes.</p>
            <p n="3">3.
<note place="margin">3. To be juſt to the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth. 1. In preſerving the liberty.</note> Be <hi>juſt</hi> to the Common-wealth:</p>
            <p n="1">1. Preſerve the <hi>publick Liberty</hi> (the inheritance of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Land) ſo farre as honeſtly you may. Your <hi>Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours,</hi> who ſate under that roof where you daily ſit, purchaſed the <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and you preſerve their memory with ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour: We owe to your Time <hi>The Petition of Right,</hi> and divers other <hi>Relaxations,</hi> and for them <hi>Poſterity</hi> will honour your memory.</p>
            <p n="2">2.
<note place="margin">2. In preferring the publick inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſe.</note> Preferre the <hi>publick Intereſſe:</hi> Be willing to be rather nothing in reputation, then that the Nation ſhould loſe hers. The brave <hi>Policratidas</hi> of <hi>Lacedemon</hi> who was ſent to the enemy with ſome others, and having made ſome <hi>Propoſitions,</hi> being demanded if they came privately, or were ſent; hee anſwered, <hi>Si impetramus, publicè Sin minùs, privatim. If wee obtaine, wee were ſent; if otherwiſe, we onely came.</hi> Let mee add, Build up the <hi>houſe of the Kingdome,</hi> rather then <hi>ciele</hi> your owne: Set up no private houſes upon the <hi>Common waſte:</hi> Hearken not to the inticements of <hi>opportunity</hi> to doe wrong. <hi>Frederick</hi> the <hi>Emperour</hi> educated in his <hi>Court</hi> the young <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſlaus,</hi> the infant-King of <hi>Hungarie</hi> and <hi>Bohemia;</hi> ſome that
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:113598:13"/>were about him perſwaded him to lay hold on that advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to joyn thoſe <hi>two Kingdomes</hi> to his; But ſaid hee, <hi>Quid ergo, Divitem potius, quàm justum Regem vulcis?</hi> What? Would you rather have a <hi>rich King,</hi> then a <hi>just one?</hi> Imply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that they muſt alſo expect the ſame from him in dealing with them, rather to fill his coffers out of their eſtates, then to yeeld them the benefit of juſt adminiſtrations. Nothing <hi>good</hi> can bee expected from a man that is onely <hi>good</hi> to <hi>himſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3.<note place="margin">3. In ſecuring the future peace.</note> Be carefull of the ſucceeding times, to ſecure the peace of them. Admit them not to <hi>trust,</hi> who have betrayed the <hi>Publick trust:</hi> Put not the Common-wealth into their hands, who have deceived or oppreſt it. Suffer mee to apply my ſelf (as I am wont) by a Storie: There was one <hi>Septimius Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binus,</hi> a man very infamous for many oppreſſions, who being acquitted under <hi>Heliogabalus,</hi> and re-admitted into the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate,</hi> (the great <hi>Parliament</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi>) when upon the choice of <hi>Alexander Severus</hi> to the Empire, the <hi>Senators</hi> entertained him with a publick Salutation and Congratulations, hee eſpy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Arabinus</hi> among them, cryed out, <hi>O numina? Arabinus non ſolùm vivit, ſed in Senatum venit. Ah, what times are theſe? What doe I ſee? Arabinus not onely lives, but ſits in Senate alſo.</hi> Through a juſt indignation hee would not endure to ſee him.</p>
            <p n="4">4.<note place="margin">4. To be juſt to friends.</note> I have yet one particular more to exhort you unto: Be <hi>just</hi> to your <hi>friends.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <note place="margin">1. To Miniſters.</note> To the <hi>Miniſters</hi> who are godly, zealous, and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onable in their function: Suffer them not to be expoſed to <hi>contempt,</hi> or <hi>want;</hi> both of which are the deſignes of ſuch as are enemies to the <hi>honour</hi> and <hi>ſucceſſe</hi> of your preſent Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels. And I the rather ſpeak of the later, becauſe of the <hi>Petition</hi> which a few dayes ſince came unto your <hi>hands,</hi> but (to the praiſe of your <hi>Equity</hi> and Wiſedome) not enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <note place="margin">2. To the honeſt party.</note> To the <hi>faithfull</hi> and <hi>honeſt party</hi> of the Land, who have ſpent their eſtates, loſt their livelihoods, ventured upon the <hi>frownes</hi> of their Prince, to ſerve the <hi>Publick</hi> and <hi>You,</hi> with all ſincerity and diligence. Let not enemies eat their bread, or
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:113598:14"/>take their trade out of their hands. <hi>Reward</hi> them, <hi>cheriſh</hi> them <hi>employ</hi> them. It was a wiſe and juſt proviſion which wee find in <hi>Plato,</hi> in his ſixth Book <hi>De Legibus: No man that ſerves the Publick, muſt ſuffer in his private eſtate, but care is to be had of him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3.
<note place="margin">3. To the Scots.</note> To our <hi>Brethren</hi> of <hi>Scotland,</hi> who are your <hi>friends</hi> by many obligations: Be <hi>just</hi> in what is due to them in the agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. I pretend not to the knowledge of any thing in this matter, beyond what you are pleaſed to let every man know in publick <hi>Inſtruments</hi> and <hi>Scripts,</hi> and think it enough onely to have intimated this among other Exhortations.</p>
            <p>And now upon the <hi>whole,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Motives of the Uſe.</note> what ſhall I ſay by way of enforce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this point? What Motives ſhall I need to uſe?</p>
            <p n="1">1.
<note place="margin">1. Juſtice ſaves from Reproach.</note> Hereby ye ſhall be kept ſafe from <hi>reproach:</hi> for <hi>righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe</hi> is a <hi>breſt plate, Epheſ.</hi> 6.14. yea, you ſhall be clothed with <hi>honour.</hi> I propoſed the 29. Chapter of <hi>Job</hi> as an example: ſee alſo in the ſame place the reward of his integrity. Hee was ſo reſpected, that <hi>when hee went out to the gate</hi> (of judgement,) <hi>the young men ſaw him, and hid themſelves, and the aged aroſe, and ſtood up: The Princes refrained talking, and laid their hand on their mouth: The Nobles held their peace, and their tongue cleaved to the roof of their mouth. When the ear heard him, it bleſſed him, and when the eye ſaw him, it gave witneſſe to him:</hi> (as when the <hi>Oratour</hi> in <hi>Athens</hi> was declaming in praiſe of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, all the eyes of the people were inſtantly faſtned upon <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtides,</hi> who ſate among the Auditors:) It followes, <hi>verſ.</hi> 21, 22, 23. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto him men gave ear, and waited, and kept ſilence at his Councell: After his words they ſpake not again, and his ſpeech dropped upon them: They waited for him as the rain, and opened their mouth wide as for the later rain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2.
<note place="margin">2. Juſtice forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies againſt at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts.</note> Hereby yee ſhall be kept ſafe from attempts. The righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous may be as bold as a Lion: Hee needs not fear any thing, that fears onely to be corrupt. Some men talk of the <hi>Conſtel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations,</hi> and what the <hi>Heavens</hi> threaten; But the <hi>Starres</hi> are no enemies to <hi>just</hi> men. It was a conceit which much pleaſed mee, when I obſerved it among the <hi>Symbols</hi> which I formerly mentioned, of <hi>Coſmus</hi> the <hi>firſt, Duke</hi> of <hi>Tuſcany:</hi> his device was, <hi>A Diana</hi> with a <hi>Serpent</hi> at her foot, (the meaning ſeems to
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:113598:14"/>be, <hi>Pureneſſe of converſation</hi> walking with <hi>wiſedome</hi>) Shee held in her hand the figure of the <hi>Conſtellation</hi> of <hi>Capricorn</hi> (which it ſeems was the <hi>Signe</hi> under which he was born, and as the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrologers</hi> would perſwade him, threatned ſome evill to him,) The word was, <hi>Integer vitae, ſceleríſque purus:</hi> Implying, that hee that is <hi>wiſe</hi> and <hi>just</hi> needs not ſtand in doubt of any thing. It is the moſt <hi>aſſured protection</hi> to be <hi>honeſt,</hi> and the moſt <hi>quick-ſighted providence</hi> to have a <hi>ſincere eye</hi> to God. Many great fiſhes that tumble in the waves, and devoure the ſhoales of the leſſer fiſh, notwithſtanding their ſtrength and quick eyes, doe many times cruſh themſelves againſt the rocks, and periſh. But the <hi>Naturaliſts</hi> tell us of one fiſh, which they call the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ranoſcope,</hi> which hath but <hi>one eye,</hi> and that in a verticall point, on the top of the head, directly <hi>upward:</hi> by which it yet avoids all rocks and dangers. 'Tis much better to have but one eye, ſo it be to heaven, in a ſincere reſpect to juſtice, then two of the beſt and ſharpeſt eyes of corrupt and worldly po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <note place="margin">3. Juſtice better then a Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving.</note> Let mee take another Motive from the day, a <hi>Day</hi> of <hi>Thanksgiving:</hi> Wee are met together to offer our praiſes unto God, and we have a large field of matter, <hi>Ten</hi> ſeverall mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies that I have mentioned in your <hi>firſt,</hi> and in your <hi>additionall Order.</hi> Wee have reaſon to be joyfull, and you have done well to appoint a <hi>Feaſt,</hi> and a <hi>ſolemn Aſſembly.</hi> But let mee tell you, that the diſpenſing of <hi>juſtice</hi> is a more acceptable ſervice to God, then a <hi>publick Thanksgiving.</hi> To which purpoſe let mee onely commend unto you that place of the Prophet, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos</hi> 5.21, 22, 23, 24. <hi>I hate, I deſpiſe your Feaſt-dayes, and I will not ſmell</hi> (ſpeaking of the Sacrifices that were offered) <hi>in your ſolemn Aſſemblies. Though yee offer me burnt-offerings, and your meat-offerings, I will not accept them, neither will I regard the peace-offerings of your fat beaſts. Take thou away from mee the noyſe of thy ſongs: For I will not hear the melody of thy viols. But let judgement run down</hi> (or roul) <hi>as waters, and righteouſneſſe as a mighty ſtream.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <note place="margin">4. The neglect of juſtice will make the ſoul tremble.</note> Laſtly, I will make bold to add this, that if any man be guilty, and his conſcience come once to be opened and convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced of <hi>injuſtice,</hi> that mans ſoul will <hi>tremble;</hi> which effect <hi>Pauls</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:113598:15"/>diſcourſe had upon <hi>Felix:</hi> the Text ſaith, <hi>Acts</hi> 24.25. <hi>As hee reaſoned of righteouſneſſe, temperance, and judgement to come, Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lix trembled.</hi> For it ſeems his own ſin came to his remembrance.</p>
            <p>I have now delivered unto you that which was in my thoughts, and in my vowes. For if I were to give a preſent ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count unto God, what I had made choice of to ſpeak, having an opportunity to ſpeak to the high Court of the <hi>Parliament of England;</hi> I would ſay, I had preached to them of <hi>righteouſneſs</hi> and <hi>equity.</hi> And for you <hi>Honourable</hi> and <hi>Renowned,</hi> I know no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more proper: I have read of an old <hi>Councellour</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> who having ſpent many yeers of ſervice in the <hi>Court,</hi> deſiring to retire himſelfe into the Countrey to enjoy the <hi>privacie</hi> that was fit for his <hi>age,</hi> and having obtained leave, before he went, the <hi>King</hi> his Maſter required him to ſet down and leave ſome <hi>advices</hi> of <hi>Government</hi> behind him: hee being unwilling, and out of his modeſt opinion of himſelfe declining it, the King would not be denied, but left with him pen and ink, and a ſheet of paper: Hee being alone, after ſome thoughts, wrote in fair legible Characters on the top of the ſheet <hi>MOD<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S,</hi> and toward the middle of it alſo <hi>MOD<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S,</hi> and at the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of the ſheet, in like-manner <hi>MOD<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S,</hi> nothing but <hi>Modus, Modus, Modus,</hi> and ſo wrapt it up, and delivered it to the King; meaning, that the beſt councell hee could give, was, that hee ſhould keep a <hi>Temper</hi> in all things. If I were thought worthy to offer an advice to ſo learned and wiſe a <hi>Body,</hi> I would write on the top of my leafe <hi>Juſtice,</hi> in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle <hi>Juſtice,</hi> and at the bottome <hi>Juſtice:</hi> According to my Text, in the reading of it which I have preferred, <hi>Juſtice, Juſtice, thou ſhalt follow,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Honoured Fathers, Renowned Patriots,</hi> I have done, when I have onely ſummed my Diſcourſe in a few words: Be <hi>juſt,</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. To your <hi>Covenant,</hi> in which yee are ſolemnly ingaged.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To the <hi>publick intereſſe,</hi> the honour and proſperity of the Nation.</p>
            <p n="3">3. To the <hi>Diſtinguiſhing principles</hi> of <hi>Proteſtancy,</hi> which you know, but I have not time to mention.</p>
            <p n="4">4. To the <hi>Miniſters</hi> that have aſſiſted with advice, with prayer, with much zeal.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:113598:15"/> 5. To our <hi>Brethren,</hi> and to the <hi>honeſt partie</hi> of the Land, who have faithfully <hi>ſerved</hi> you, and <hi>ſuffered</hi> much for you.</p>
            <p>Then,</p>
            <p n="1">1. You ſhall <hi>live,</hi> comfortably, and in our <hi>hearts;</hi> yea, and hereafter in <hi>Story.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. You ſhall poſſeſſe and <hi>inherit</hi> your good <hi>land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. You ſhall rejoyce in the firm and pleaſant <hi>amity</hi> of your <hi>neighbour Kingdome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Your enemies ſhall <hi>lie</hi> unto you, and lick the duſt.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Rome</hi> ſhall <hi>ſhake,</hi> and that <hi>Antichriſt</hi> ſhall become a trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling prophet to himſelfe of his own approaching ruine. <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, Juſtice ſhalt thou follow, that thou mayeſt live, and inherit the Land, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
